This is a work of fiction.
Any resemblance to real persons, groups or events is purely coincidental.
Hey everyone! Nothin' to do?
おまえら 暇か
Quiz Trial
How'd you like to be the quiz king of Kamiyama City?!
神山市のクイズ王に
なりたいか
Smash through the prelims and aim for the top!
予選ぐらいは突破…するぞ
Quiz Trial Seven!
クイズ トライアル セブン
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
KamiGami
Today is a real mess, but I get over it with a sigh
複雑に構えた今日が 息を呑んで澄ましてる
You get the idea, right?
身に覚えあるだろう 君はどうしたい
What do you wanna do?
You act as if nothing happened
何もなかったそぶりで  かばう痛みはもう
As if your heart didn't ache
It almost feels encouraging,
心強いくらいに 急かすんだ
the way you're rushing me
Hold it and let it overflow
掴んでこぼして 不完全な僕たちが
We're all imperfect
光って見えない 未来の自分を創れるなら
I can't see it well in the light,
but if we can change our future selves
目覚めるまま走れ 蜃気楼を追い越して
Wake up and run
Go and surpass the mirage
変わりたいまま走れ 自由な違和感で
Try to change and run
with the discomfort of freedom
届きそうな輝きと今を選んでいこう
We can reach that shining light
Follow it into the present
飛びたつ手を知らない
Don't hesitate to act
Deep or quick, just keep breathing
深い 浅い 呼吸を重ねて
Hyouka
Quiz Trial
Dead at Dusk
日暮现残骸
Question one!
第一問です
金剛石とはダイアモンドのことですが
The word "kongouseki" means diamond,
and the word "rokujuugyoku" means emerald.
緑柱玉とはエメラルドのことである
○でしょうか×でしょうか
Is this true? Or false?
あれ×だろう
第一問目はこんなもんかなあ
So that's the first question, huh?
The answer is...
答えは
True!
○
真のデーターベースが誰か
I'll show you who's the real database here.
教えてやる
There's less and less of you remaining!
いよいよ人数がしぼられてきました
これが予選最後の問題となるでしょうか
Could this be the last problem of the prelims?
では第七問
Let's see the seventh question!
The word "darui" originates from the English word "dull".
ダルイは英語のダルが語源である
Is this true? Or false?
○でしょうか×でしょうか
I don't know...
どっちだろう
It feels like it might have originated there...
語源っぽい気もするけど
Right, Mayaka?
ね 摩耶花
What do you think?
どっちだと思う
I'd say it's true.
○…かな
答えは
The answer is...
You've built enough suspense already!
溜めなくていいから
×
False!
The prelims are over!
予選終了
正解の方おめでとうございます
Congratulations to the people who got it right!
We're holding the finals over here!
決勝戦はこちらの壇上で行います
さ どうぞ
Finals
よお
Hey!
That's quite an outfit, Fukube.
福部 おまえ面白い格好してるな
一人目のファイナリストです
クラスと名前をどうぞ
Do I know this guy?
誰だっけ
Ah, thanks.
三年E組み清水紀子です
まあね
You didn't notice me at all, did you?
おまえ ぜんぜん俺に気づいてなかっただろう
クイズに集中してですか
I was focusing on the quiz, you see.
自信のほどはいかがです
Oh, that's who it is.
あっ思い出した
So, Tani, how is the Go Club?
で 谷君 囲碁部はどう
すみませんちょっと緊張しています
うん 囲碁部か
The Go Club? Something interesting happened lately.
では 二人目のファイナリストの紹介です
ちょっと面白い話があってな
クラスと名前を
二年Ｃ組み後藤直樹です
Wanna hear more?
聞くか
And if we could have our third finalist...
ええ では 三人目のファイナリストの方
あっ はいはい
Oh, over here!
Let's get going.
ほら 行こう
はあ なんか 頭に土星乗ってますよ
Oh, you've got something on your head!
Your name and class, please!
クラスとお名前をどうぞ
I'm Fukube Satoshi from the Classics Club!
古典部の 福部里志です
Sorry?
は
The Classics Club!
古典部でーす
Whoa, there's a Classics Club?
へえ 古典部なんてあるんですね
この学校 変な部活多いですもんね
This school has all kinds of weird clubs, doesn't it?
Yeah!
ねぇ そう 変な部活なんです
It's a weird club all right!
After all, even its purpose is unclear!
直せ 活動目的が不明なんです
Huh? Really?
へえ そうなんですか
Our club tradition is to publish a yearly anthology, which we've done again this year.
文集を作る部活だってことはわかったので
作って見たんです
そうしたら我ながらすごいことになれました
It turned out great!
力入ってますよ
We really gave it our all!
確かに 力入ってるなあ
It certainly did turn out great.
部数は
Great in number.
We solved the great mystery of the Kan'ya Fair!
なんとこのカンヤ祭の 重大な秘密を解き明かしたんです
What's that?
ほう それは
The origin of the name "Kan'ya Fair" itself!
カンャ祭の名前の由来ですよ
It wasn't just a simple shortening of "Kamiyama High Culture Fair" to "Kan'ya Fair" after all!
神山高校文化祭が 詰ってカンヤ祭
なんて簡単なもんじゃありません
And the Classics Club...
古典部はそれを
solved that mystery!
突き止めました
So what did you find out?
その由来とは
If you want to know...
それは
Buy our anthology!
買ってください
For just 200 yen,
ただ二百円で
you can discover the amazing secrets buried within Kan'ya Fair's 45-year history for yourselves!
神山高校文化祭 四十五年の秘密が あなたの手に
Our anthology, Hyouka, is on sale in the Earth Sci. Prep Room on the fourth floor of the auxiliary building!
文集氷菓は 特別棟四階 地学準備室で 絶賛発売中です
I managed to catch the whole crowd's attention.
アピール成功だ
It doesn't even matter if I win or lose now.
もう優勝なんて どうでもいい
Oreki...
折木さん
どうだった
How did you go?
Tanabe said we should ask the other clubs to sell it for us.
田辺さん曰く
ほかの部の売り場においてもらうのはいいそうです
それで
So I wanted to ask Irisu for help,
入須さんのところにご相談に行こうとしたんですけど
but I just couldn't make it...
辿りつけなくて
I get the idea.
まあ さしはつくが
This is bad.
困りました
Satoshi did a pretty good job promoting the club.
里志の宣伝 なかなか面白かったぞ
Promoting?
宣伝
そうです 確か 壁新聞部が号外を出していました
That's right!
The News Poster Club was planning to release a special edition!
I'll go ask them to write about the Classics Club too!
古典部を取り上げてもらえないか聞いてみます
She's always in a rush.
忙しないな
News Poster Club
Information please!
Excuse me!
すみません
なにか用事かな
Can I help you?
Good afternoon, Tougaito.
こうにちは 遠垣内さん
Could you write about the Classics Club?
古典部を 取り上げていただけませんか
I don't really get what you mean.
意味はよくわからないんだけど
すみません
Oh, I'm sorry.
I was wondering if you'd be able to put an advert for the Classics Club in your newspaper.
壁新聞の記事に 古典部の宣伝を載せていただけないか
お願いにきたんですが
うん…ええと 俺…もう部員じゃないんだ
Well...
I'm not actually in the club anymore.
I'm in third year, so I retired.
三年だから引退したんのよ
あっ すみません
I'm sorry. Then could you introduce me to your juniors?
では 後輩の方を紹介していただけないでしょうか
I could, but I'm not sure if they can help you.
それはいいけど 無駄だと思うな
We release a new special every two hours, so our schedule is quite tight.
二時間に一枚号外を出すから
スケジュールは予め決まってるんだ
載せるのは無理ですか
So there's no way we can get an ad in the paper?
I didn't say that.
無理とは言わないよ
We have some free space in the afternoon on the second day,
二日目の昼以降なら 紙面に余裕もとってあるけど
カンヤ際には五十からの団体が出展してるから
but there are over fifty clubs doing something for the Kan'ya Fair
so we're prioritizing stuff worth paying attention to.
注目すべきところを優先して載せるんだ
This might sound harsh, but the Classics Club has only done an anthology, right?
こう言っちゃなんだけと
古典部って確か 文集しか出してないだろう
B-But it contains...
で…でも 文集の内容は
Every club is serious about what they write about.
内容はどこの部活も真剣だよ
みんなの注目を集めるネタがあれば
Nonethtless, if you have something worthy of everyone's attention,
I'll ask the others to write about you.
こっちから頼んで取り上げさせてもらうけどね
Something worthy?
ネタですか
I see. Thanks for your time.
分かりました
お手間を取らせてすみませんでした
なにか面白い話が持ち上がったら
If you find something interesting, let me know.
もう一回来てよ
I might be able to help you out.
力になれるかもしれないし
Eru!
エル
はは かほさん
Kaho!
Long time no see.
久しぶり
Is old Mr. Juumonji still in good health?
十文字のおじ様はそのばお元気ですか
Yeah, he's still going strong.
もうすっかりね
But you look troubled. What's wrong?
それより妙に暗いけど どうしたの
A few things led to another...
少し…いろいろありまして
ま 入って なんなら占ってみようか
Come on in, then. I'll tell your fortune.
This is really amazing.
相変わらずすごいですね
えっと では タロットでお願いします
Um...
I'd like a tarot reading, please.
ああ それはだめなんだ
That won't do.
へっ どうしてですか
Why is that?
Eru, you like stuff like this, right?
エル
こういうの好きだっけ
The Fortune Teller Club
has lost the Wheel of Fortune.
Juumonji
What's that?
これは
I'm doing this on my own, so sometimes I need to step out for a moment.
あたし一人でやってるから
結構席を外すんだ
One time, I arrived back to find the Wheel of Fortune missing from the tarot deck.
ちょっと離れて戻ってきたら
タロットから運命の輪が無くなってったの
That card was in its place.
で 代わりにそのカードがおいてあった
Juumonji
十文字って なんでかほさんの名字が書いてあるんでしょう
But why Juumonji? That's your family name, right?
Yeah... I don't get it.
さあ なんでだろうね
Did you find the missing card?
そのなくなったカードは 見つかったんですか
This note was there as well,
こんなのも残ってたし
I'll return it after the Culture Fair.
so I think it'll come back to me eventually.
戻ってくるとは思うんだけど
That's not what you'd expect from a thief.
泥棒にしては本当に風変わりですね
じゃ 最後にもう一つ見せようかなあ
Let me show you one more thing.
このシオリは なにか特別な
Is there something unusual about that guide?
中身は出回ってるのと同じ
It's identical to all the other ones they're giving out.
そのカードと一緒に置いてあったの
I found it alongside that notice.
It was left open at the last page, showing the list of participating clubs.
最後の 参加団体一言コメントのページを開いてね
Could that mean something?
なにか 意味があるのでしょうか
Who knows? I'd be happy just to get my Wheel of Fortune back.
さあね
私は運命の輪が無事に帰ってくればそれでいいんだけどね
The Fortune Teller Club
has lost the Wheel of Fortune.
Juumonji
さあ いよいよクライマックスです
All right, time for the high point of the day!
清水さん後藤さんが五ポイント
Shimizu and Gotou have five points each,
そして
and Fukube and Tani have six points each, putting them in equal first place.
谷さん福部さんが六ポイントで
二人は王手をかけています
How will this grand battle end?
この決着の行方はどうなるのでしょうか
皆様もご声援よろしくお願いします
Please lend them your support!
Let's see the next question!
では 次の問題です
Here we go!
いきます
The formula for calculating the surface area of a sphere is...
球の表面積を求める公式は４πｒ二乗
Four pi times r squared—
おほ 早い
That was fast!
Are you sure about this? I haven't finished asking the question yet!
問題はまだ終わっていませんが 大丈夫でしょうか
Yes.
はい
Then Shimizu, please give us your answer!
それでは清水さん
お答えください
Four-thirds pi times r cubed!
三分の４πｒ三乗
Correct!
正解
The formula for calculating the surface area of a sphere is four pi times r squared.
球の表面積を求める公式は４πｒ二乗です
Given that, what's the formula for calculating its volume?
では 体積を求める公式をお答えください
答えは 三分の４πｒ三乗
The correct answer is four-thirds pi times r cubed.
Well done!
お見事です これで清水さんも王手
Shimizu joins the other two in first place with a tied score of six points!
三名の方が六ポイントになります
What an amazing dead heat!
すばらしい デッドヒートになってます
後藤さんも 頑張れ
Do your best, Gotou!
Now, onto the next problem! Here we go!
では 次の問題です
いきます
I'm sure you've all heard of the Kamiyama High Student Council president.
神山高校の生徒会長のフルネーム
But what's his full name?
を答えてください
Huh?
あれ…
Yes, Shimizu?
はい 清水さん
Kagayama Moriyoshi!
陸山 宗芳
Get some fiber in your diet...
その溜めはもういいよ
正解
Correct!
クイズ トライアル セブン 優勝者は三年Ｅ組み清水紀子です
Hey, Fukube.
おい 福部
Well, that was a shame.
いや 惜しかったね お互い
Yeah. We're tied.
だな 引き分けってことだ
So? What's up?
で なにか
ありがとうございます
囲碁部の面白い話の続きだよ
Something happened to the Go Club.
A bunch of Go stones were stolen.
碁石がいくつか盗まれたんだ
清水さん 前にきてください
Not just lost, but stolen?
無くなったんじゃなくて 盗まれたんだ
We found a note left in the box claiming responsibility. It said, "I've taken a few stones from the Go Club."
碁笥に「囲碁部から碁石をいただいた」って犯行声明が入ってた
We don't use them all, so even if they took ten or so we probably wouldn't notice.
全部を使う訳じゃないから
十個くらい持っていかれても気付かんのだろうな
Why would anyone steal something like that?
そんなもの盗んでどうするのかな
そりゃもちろん 五目並べでもするんだろう
Maybe they want to play five-in-a-row.
他の部員の冗談でしょ
It must just be a prank by one of the other members.
それじゃ
See you.
Wait a moment!
待て待て
I can't let this end in a draw!
引き分けのままじゃ、気が済まん
This is a battle of wits! Where are you competing next?
勝負しようぜ
次はどこに出る？
At the cooking event tomorrow, I guess.
明日のお料理研かな
Okay!
OK この勝負の白黒はそこでつけよう
We'll finish our battle then!
期待してるぞ
I'm looking forward to it!
Here we go again...
無粋だね
I could live without Tani's challenges.
谷君との勝負は興味ないんだけど
I wonder if Houtarou's doing all right.
奉太郎は真面目にやってるかな
Are you open?
やってる？
Y-Yeah, we're open!
や やってますよ
This is the one that explains how the Kan'ya Fair got its name, right?
カンヤ祭の語源が載ってるのって これ？
Can I just read it here?
立ち読みしていい？
Nope.
だめです
It's only 200 yen, so please buy one.
二百円なんで 買ってください
We've got so many left I could cry.
あまりまくって泣きそうなんです
By the way, your fly's open.
先輩 前 開いてますよ
ああ 破けてる 参ったな
Damn, the zip's broken.
Try using this.
ちょっと使ってみてください
Oh, good thing you had that! Thanks!
おお～ よくこんなの持ってたな
助かった
礼だ やる
My thanks. Here.
An airgun?
エアガンですか
A water gun!
水鉄砲だよ
We're selling fried potatoes at the acting club,
園芸部で焼き芋をやってるんだ
and putting out fires with buckets is just boring.
火を消すのがバケツだと芸がないだろ？
Won't you be needing this, then?
じゃ これ要るんじゃないですか
That's just my sidearm.
そいつはサイドアームでね
This is my main.
メインアームはこれ
It's an AK.
AK-7
Wonderful.
さいで
Later! Thanks!
じゃあな サンキュー
A Glock 17, huh?
グロックの17か
秋分
阴阳相半也
Autumn Equinox
When light and dark are in balance.
Hyouka
Welcome to
the Manga Lab
To begin with,
そもそも この文集が失敗だったのよ
Zeamiz
this anthology is a failure.
No one's coming here!
だーれも来ないじゃない
We should draw a poster or something and attract customers!
今からポスターでも描いて
お客さんを呼んだ方がいいって
But we all decided we'd do it like this.
でも こういう雰囲気で行こうって みんなで決めたし
Why are you looking at me?
なんで私を見るかな
Manga Lab
Anthology on sale
100 reviews
of old manga!
Who'd want to read a hundred manga reviews? That's just boring!
漫画のレビュー百本なんて
そんな堅苦しいもの 誰が読むの？
Kawachi, you should...
あの 河内さん もう
What's the point of reviewing them to begin with?
大体レビューなんかしたって意味ないわよ
It's just a waste of time. Right?
無駄よ 無駄 ねえ
W-Well...
え まあ
I hope Fuku will believe me, at least.
福ちゃんは信じてくれるかな
I really tried to take this seriously.
本当におとなしくしようとしてたんだよ
Why is it a waste of time,
無駄ってどういうことですか 先輩
exactly?
It's all about the readers.
要は読み手の問題だからよ
The readers?
読み手の？
That's right.
そうよ
Manga are fun, but they're all basically the same thing.
漫画の面白さは本来みんーな同じなの
Regardless of the author?
誰が描いてもですか
Yeah.
そうよ
Then how do you tell what's good and what's bad?
なら 面白いかどうかの差はどこで出来るんですか
Don't you get it, Ibara?
わからないの 伊原
That's where the reader comes in.
それが読み手なのよ
It's just a matter of how finely honed your critical instincts are.
結局 読み手の面白さを感じ取るアンテナが高いか低いか
それだけなのよ
And those who don't have that can't
appreciate manga for what they are?
つまり アンテナの低い人には面白さが伝わらないってことですか
Exactly.
そうよ
That's why reviews are a waste of time.
だからレビューなんて無駄だって言ってるの
We should just read what we like
私たちは好きなものだけ読んで けらけら笑ってればいいのよ
and have fun doing so.
You're saying all manga are the same?
漫画がどれも同じだなんて そんなこと絶対納得できない
There's no way I could accept that!
I'm not gonna lose this one!
負けるもんか
Then tell me,
じゃ 先輩 その理屈なら
By that reasoning, does that mean there are no exceptional manga either?
いわゆる名作って言われるものもないってことですよね
No, there are many such greats.
名作はあるよ
How do you define "great"?
定義はなんですか
Anything that continues to be appreciated over many years by many people.
「ながーい年月」「たくさんの鑑賞者」っていう篩に
かけられ続けて残ったもの
That's greatness.
これが名作よ
That's not it.
違います
Truly exceptional manga have been exceptional since the beginning!
名作は最初から名作として生まれてくるんです
Unless they've withstood the test of time, they're only exceptional in your opinion.
時間に淘汰されてないものなんて
それこそあんたの主観じゃない
You're wrong!
違います！
Am I?
何が
The only problem here is your lack of experience!
これは経験の問題です
You just haven't been overcome by anything truly amazing yet!
先輩は「これってすごい」っていうものに
ガツンとやられたことがないだけです
へえ 言ってくれるじゃない
I see someone grew a sharp tongue.
There's a vast difference in skill and talent between authors!
描き手の才能や技術の差は絶対にあります
Tell me, did you read the Dead at Dusk manga that was sold at last year's culture fair?
先輩 去年この学校の文化祭で売られた
「夕べには骸に」って漫画 読みましたか
No.
知らないよ
I'll bring it tomorrow, then.
じゃあ 明日持ってきます
If even that fails to convince you, I'll have nothing more to say.
それで納得してもらえないなら
私にはもう言葉がありません
So much for selling Hyouka here...
これで氷菓を置いてもらう話 できなくなちゃったな
ありがとうございました
What's going on?
何 これ
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ
Not to be missed! Fighting now!
Battle of the Maidens
in the Manga Lab
See manga theory hotly debated!
The Priestess vs The Hermaphrodite!
Battle of the Maidens?
乙女の戦い
Um...
あの
Yes?
はい
What's that?
これは？
Sorry, they just finished.
もう終わりました
But we'll be holding another one tomorrow,
明日はまたやりますので ぜひ来て下さいね
so I hope you'll drop by!
So, what did you think? How was my promotion?
で どうだった？ 僕のアピール
Did it do any good?
少しは役に立ったかな
Yeah, kinda.
ああ まあな
We sold fourteen copies.
十四部売れた
え 本当に？
Really?!
Advertising is more effective than I thought.
宣伝は案外効くらしい
滑り出しとしては上々だね
That's a great start!
Let's keep it up tomorrow as well!
明日も一丁頑張ろうかな
I've got a good feeling about that cooking contest!
お料理のコンテストは自信あるんだ
The three-man team event?
あの三人一組のやつ？
は？ 三人一組？
What? You need three people?!
Seriously?
本当に
So much for General Affairs being familiar with the events.
総務員なのにイベントを把握してないのか
I'm sorry.
すみません
I wasn't able to get us another location to sell from,
売り場を広げてもらうことも
and I had no luck getting the News Poster club to write about us.
壁新聞に取り上げていただくこともできませんでした
Don't worry about it.
気にするな
But...
でも 気になることがあったんですが
There was one thing I couldn't stop thinking about...
You couldn't?
気になる？
Actually, I guess it doesn't matter.
いえ やっぱり気になりません
Glad to hear that.
大変よろしい
Look! It doesn't say anything about it being a three-man team!
ほら 三人一組なんて書いてないよ
I'm sure of it. I heard people from the Cooking Club talking about it.
間違いないよ お料理研の子がそう言ってるの聞いたもん
That's a shame.
誤算だ
I thought I'd be able to enter alone.
一人でも出られると思ったのに
By the way, Mayaka, how did you go at the Manga Lab?
そういや 摩耶花 漫研はどうだった？
Don't ask.
何もなかったわよ
Mayaka, Chitanda, would you enter the cooking contest with me?
摩耶花 千反田さん
一緒にお料理研のコンテストに出てくれないかな
I'll ask the president to let me go.
抜けられるように部長に相談はできるけど
If if it means we can promote our club, I definitely want to!
宣伝になるなら ぜひ出たいです
Okay! Our hearts are as one!
よし ひとまず望みは繋がったね
How badly did you want to enter?
どんだけ出たかったんだ
I'm pretty confident about my cooking.
料理にはちょっと自信があるんだ
There's no way I'd miss a exciting contest like that!
こんなに楽しそうな大会 出ないではないよ
To all students and guests,
全校生徒の皆さん 及びご来場の皆様
with this announcement the first day of the Kan'ya Fair has come to a close.
この放送を持ちまして カンヤ祭の一日目を終了します
All students not on council duty should now make their way to the gates.
あのう 折木さん
Oreki,
did you...
もしかして これ
Um... Well...
Never mind!
いえ なんでもないです
どこだろう
Where is it?
It's not here...
ない
Oh come on, where are you?
どこに行ったんだろう
Dead at Dusk
Body Talk
I'll take this instead...
代わりにこれを
No, I can't do that!
いや だめだ
Town
Info
I can't find it...
どこにもない
なんで
Why?
The situation is unscientific
状況は非科学的に 感情のモンタージュ
A montage of emotions
Who's calling who?
誰が誰を呼んでる
You look away when our eyes are about to meet
振り向けば逃げてく視線（感じる）
I can feel it
Am I just imagining things? It's so cold of you
気のせいじゃつれないよ アンテナは才能って言うでしょ
It takes talent to read minds
You know
だって（だって） 知りたい（君は違うの？）
I wanna know
Don't you?
I'll fix the fire of youth in your heart while I can
青春の温度差 今のうち正してあげるよ
If we can do it today why leave it for tomorrow
明日解決するなら 今でもよくない？
I want to solve your mystery
君のミステリー解いてみたい
Look for the back of the boy, burdened with secrets
少年の秘密めいた背中探せ（今日も）
Even today
You are a fantasy and I'm drawn to you
君はファンタジー 惹かれてゆくよ（ずるい）
This growing curiosity
膨らんだ好奇心 とりたくはないのに
There's no twist in the story
I can't stop thinking about it
気になるよ 興味深い どうして
It's so interesting
But why?
Next time: Wild Fire.
次回 ワイルドファイア
Wild Fire